<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Ramblings on Aaroh&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ramblings on Aaroh&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.139.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:11:15 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/ramblings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Missing Out on The Old Internet</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/the-old-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:11:15 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/the-old-internet/</guid>
      <description>One of the reasons I decided to start writing a blog this year was because I was inspired by an old blog I found while watching Code Geass all the way back in December last year. I wanted to see other people&amp;#39;s opinions on Code Geass, and I stumbled upon a seemingly &lt;em&gt;ancient&lt;/em&gt; blog that chronicled the release of every new episode of CG while it was &lt;em&gt;airing&lt;/em&gt;. Something about the blog really pulled me in. I read some other posts on that blog from that era—mostly about releases of new techonology—and it transported me to a bygone era of the internet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Review of Org Roam and Org Roam UI</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/org-roam-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 22:04:12 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/org-roam-review/</guid>
      <description>I have been using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.orgroam.com/&#34;&gt;Org Roam&lt;/a&gt; package on emacs on and off for the last semester or so for taking notes for various subjects including compilers, point set (and a little bit of algebraic) topology, abstract algebra, some measure theory, machine learning, and even neuroevolution. Org roam is based on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten&#34;&gt;zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; philosophy of notetaking, which has been explored and talked about by many people on the internet, so I won&amp;#39;t go into that here. Instead, I have gathered some of my thoughts after some use of org roam and I will be writing them here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Utter Disappointment with Trigun</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/trigun-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 12:03:11 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/ramblings/trigun-review/</guid>
      <description>When you listen to the &lt;em&gt;Trigun&lt;/em&gt; OP, you are electrified. The energetic guitar riffs, combined with the cool visuals that make the main character look like a badass, really got me pumped for the show ahead of me. Add to that the near-legendary reputation &lt;em&gt;Trigun&lt;/em&gt; has garnered on internet Anime spaces, and you have a show that may only live up to its expectations through incredible quality and depth. &lt;em&gt;Trigun&lt;/em&gt; is neither of those. In fact, it&amp;#39;s not even a good show.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
